Hello everybody and welcome to
English Pod. My name is Marco. My name is
Catherine and we hope by now you're
very excited about football or soccer.
This is the World Cup time
of year so this comes every
four years actually and
we've got a lesson all about it.
That's right. So as everyone may or
may not have heard, we are actually in the
middle of the World Cup and as you
say, it's a football or soccer competition.
Now soccer is only
used in the United States.
That's right. It's using the United States
although football can be confusing in a
place like Australia where they have two
different games that are called football.
That's right. So it's a little bit difficult at
times to tell someone that you play football and they
think you play American football or Australian
football or soccer. So it's a little bit confusing.
It can be. Alright so we have a great
lesson all about the World Cup. We're going
to explain a little bit and so let's listen
to the dialogue for the very first time.
What are you doing?
What am I doing?
What am I doing? Don't
you know what day it is? No.
It's only the day when the world's biggest
sporting event is kicking off. What?
The World Cup. The
first match is today.
It's Mexico versus South Africa.
It's going to be a really good match.
Both teams have a very strong offense and
have skilled players. I think that's South
Africa will probably dominate the first half
since they are the host country and all.
I have no idea what
you're talking about.
The only sporting event we
watch at home is the Super Bowl.
This is bigger than the Super Bowl
man. Teams from 32 countries compete
against each other every four
years and fight to win that trophy.
They first start in a group stage with
eight groups. Each group having four teams.
The top two teams pass on
to an elimination stage before
going on to the semi-finals
and the corner finals.
Sounds interesting but soccer doesn't
really appeal to me. Are you kidding?
Over 700 million people watch the
final match of the 2006 World Cup.
It's a very exciting and
nerve-wracking sport. Each nation is
cheering on their team hoping
they will become the next champion.
So far Brazil is the
team with the most
titles under their belt.
They're really good.
All I know about soccer is that you
can't use your hands and that players
are always falling down trying
to get a free kick or penalty kick.
It seems like a sissy sport to me.
Whatever.
I'm going to go watch the opening match.
Alright we're back so
obviously two people discussing
or fighting over the
World Cup and in soccer.
One of them doesn't really like
it. But he came up with some really
interesting points and explained
a couple of interesting things.
So let's take a look at some of
that vocab on language take away.
Language take away.
So okay the very first
phrase here is a very
important one we're
talking about sports.
This game is called a sporting event.
That's right so a sporting event
is an event I guess you would
say is a performance or something
that happens occasionally.
But related to sports.
That's right so an event can
be a game itself or a tournament.
You've heard maybe of
well the Ueifa Cup that's the
European Federation of
Football or whatever it is.
So basically you have this tournament
for European soccer teams but World
Cup is also an event and a very
important game could also be an event.
So this basically means a sporting
match or a sporting competition.
That's right now it may sound confusing
as to why you put the ING in sport.
It should be maybe sports
event or sport event but I'm
not really sure why we had
the gerund to sporting event.
We always just say it
this way it's a set phrase
so let's remember
that it's sporting event.
This is the world's most important
sporting event for example.
Okay very good now we went in we talked
about the first match Mexico versus South
Africa and they're talking about the teams
and how they both have a very strong offense.
Okay so offense is
a part of the team.
Basically it's a group of
players who are trying to score.
That's right.
So when you're good at
offense it means you're good
at scoring and the
opposite of offense is what?
Defense.
So offense defense.
You can say they have
a very strong defense.
That means that it's very hard
to score against them because
their defenders, their goal
is they're all very strong.
That's right.
So we're talking about an offense and a
defense both very important parts of a team.
And so the guy continued and
made a little bit of a prediction
saying that South Africa will
probably dominate the first half.
Okay so you know that football
matches are split into halves.
You have first half and second half.
To dominate here means to
be stronger than someone else.
So to control the ball or
to have possession or to
be the one that is the
strongest team on the field.
That's right.
So you can dominate by
having a very strong defense or
you can dominate by having
a very strong offense or both.
Dominate means be stronger than.
That's right.
Okay now let's move on to the
other guy who doesn't really like soccer.
And he says I have no idea
what you're talking about.
All I know is that I watch the Super Bowl.
Okay now this is a very
American thing, the Super Bowl.
That's right.
We mentioned earlier that in America most
people call the game soccer, not football.
Well that's because in America we
have a different game called football.
That's right.
And so the Super Bowl is like the most
important game in the football world.
It's the game that happens every
year at the very end of the season.
That's right.
So this is what we usually
call American football.
So you've probably seen it on TV as well.
And the Super Bowl
is basically the name of
the final sporting event
of American football.
Just like we have World
Cup we have the Super Bowl.
And the winner of the Super
Bowl is the best team that year.
That's right.
All right so now let's go on to explain a
little bit about how the World Cup works.
The guy went on to explain that
there are 32 countries competing.
Basically we have three
parts and elimination
stage, a semi-finals
and quarterfinals.
Okay so basically this
describes the different levels
because obviously 32 teams
can't compete for one trophy.
At first you have to
make the numbers smaller.
So 32 becomes 16 becomes
8 becomes 4 becomes 2.
That's right.
And so we have different groups for these.
The first one is the elimination stage
when some teams lose and they go home.
That's right.
And after that then
we have a quarterfinals.
So what is quarterfinals?
The quarterfinals are
when you have eight
teams that are basically
the top eight teams of
the competition and they will
play against one other opponent.
So the winner passes on to the next
stage which would be the semi-finals.
Well the math makes sense because
quarter has to do with four right?
That's right.
So in the quarterfinals
eight teams become four.
And in the semi-finals
four teams become two.
That's right.
And then what happens
after the semi-finals?
And then we have the final.
We're basically the two
top teams will compete
against each other and
there will be one champion.
USA.
And this is when it gets
very nationalistic people.
I'm very proud of their countries.
Of course of course.
And so this basically is what
happens and how we get our champion.
And well now let's
explain a little bit very
quickly about two things
that happen in the game.
During gameplay when we
have a free kick and a penalty kick.
Okay.
So a kick you know you just kick the ball.
But sometimes when the
ball goes out of bounds
or when a player is
injured or there's a foul,
then that player or his
teammate can take a special kick.
All right.
And so a free kick is
just a kick from anywhere.
A free kick is a kick
that you get basically
according to the referee who
says, "Okay, stop the game.
He's going to kick
from inside the lines.
" That's right.
So wherever you are
fouled, wherever somebody
maybe hit you wrong or
something happened from
that position you will kick freely
towards the goal or wherever you want.
You can pass to your other players as well.
That's right.
But a penalty kick is
a bit different because
you have to be in a
special place when you do it.
That's right.
A penalty kick is when you
are fouled inside the box
what they call is an area
very close to the goalie.
So if you commit a foul there
then the other player will receive
a penalty kick and it will
just be him against the goalie.
And he must kick the ball.
I think it's approximately
10 meters if I'm not mistaken.
Yes.
And this is why it's very
dangerous because you're
so close to the goalie
and no one can stop you.
And so when fouls
happen inside that special
box, it's usually bad
news for the goalie.
Yeah, of course.
So this is what happens during a penalty
kick and basically you have no defenders.
So it's just you, the
goalie and it can get
as you said very
complicated for the goalie.
So we've taken a look at a lot
of things on language takeaway.
Let's move on now to three
phrases on the fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Okay.
So this is a great
word to describe how I
felt last week when I
watched the England vs.
America match.
I thought it was a nerve-wracking game.
That's right.
And we heard this in the dialogue, right?
Yeah, you said it was a very
nerve-wracking game or the dialogue.
The guy said it's a very exciting
and nerve-wracking sport.
So if something's
nerve-wracking, what does it mean?
Well, basically if you break
it down, nerves are those
things in your body and
your skin that make you feel.
So if someone hurts you, you
feel it because of your nerves.
So something that is
nerve-wracking makes you nervous.
It makes you anxious.
It makes you feel very sensitive.
That's right.
So of course the sporting
event is so exciting and
you're worried that your
country or your team will lose.
That you're very nervous
and you're very excited.
You're very anxious.
A lot of things are going on.
Maybe you're sweating.
Maybe you're drinking a lot.
You don't want to know.
You don't want to see your team
lose and so you get very nervous.
That's right.
And now of course if your
team is in the World Cup, you
are cheering on for your team
or you're cheering them on.
Okay, so this is an
interesting phrase because
maybe you've heard
the word to cheer before.
Go team, go team.
This is cheering.
But we often say I want to cheer him on.
Okay, so this on to me means like
I want to cheer him on to victory.
I want to push them towards some goal.
And so you hear this a lot.
Let's cheer them on or he
was really cheering me on.
Made me feel good.
Motivating you.
So to cheer someone on, cheer them on.
All right.
So obviously this is why
we have cheer leaders, right?
Girls that give me an eight.
Give me a B.
These are the girls or the group
of girls that cheer teams on.
Or men too.
I've seen male cheer leaders.
That's true.
All right.
When we talked about Brazil, they are the
team with the most titles under their belt.
Okay, we're not talking
about a real belt here, are we?
No, no.
Under your belt or under
their belt in this case means
that in their history,
they have the most titles.
That's right.
I think it may come from a
boxing or one of those sports
where you actually wear
a belt that says your title.
And I think, if I'm
mistaken, sometimes boxing
belt will have various
titles on the belt.
Right.
The championship belts.
Because they wear it after Brazil.
I've never heard that before,
but it does make sense.
But the important thing to remember here is
that it's not just sports, you could say,
he has 10 years of experience
in marketing under his belt.
That's right.
That means he's experienced at marketing.
So that's right.
As you said, you can
use it for work experience.
But for titles in work, or
maybe in education, you
can say he's got three
masters degrees under his belt.
All right.
So a lot of great stuff there.
We've taken a look at a lot of vocab.
So I think we should
listen to our dialogue again.
And we'll be back to
talk a little bit more.
What are you doing?
What am I doing?
Don't you know what day it is?
No.
It's only the day when the world's
biggest sporting event is kicking off.
What?
The World Cup.
The first match is today.
It's Mexico versus South Africa.
It's going to be a really good match.
Both teams have a very strong
offense and have skilled players.
I think that South Africa
will probably dominate the
first half since they're
the host country and all.
I have no idea what you're talking about.
The only sporting event we
watch at home is the Super Bowl.
This is bigger than the Super Bowl, man.
Teams from 32 countries
compete against each other
every four years and
fight to win that trophy.
They first start in a group stage with
eight groups, each group having four teams.
The top two teams pass on
to elimination stage before
going on to the semi-finals
and the quarter-finals.
Sounds interesting, but soccer
doesn't really appeal to me.
Are you kidding?
The 700 million people watch the
final match of the 2006 World Cup.
It's a very exciting and
nerve-wracking sport.
Each nascent is cheering on their team,
hoping they will become the next champion.
So far, Brazil is the team with
the most titles under their belt.
They're really good.
All I know about soccer is that you
can't use your hands and that players
are always falling down trying
to get a free kick or penalty kick.
It seems like a sissy sport to me.
Whatever.
I'm going to go watch the opening match.
It's a real judge for shopping.
All right, so the World
Cup, as we said, it gathers
over 100 million people
to watch the final in 2006.
Now, this sport is not very
popular in North America.
It's not, well, that's not totally true
because Mexicans really follow football.
That's right.
But I think in America, in United States,
it is one of the less popular sports.
I was thinking the other day, maybe
number five on our list of popular sports.
Maybe because, well, you
have American football, the NFL.
You have Major League Baseball,
you have the NBA, you have the NHL.
And I think maybe before
soccer, you probably
either have golf or
tennis before soccer.
Even though the United States does
have its own Major League Soccer.
Yep, MLS, Major League
Soccer, and my hometown
team is Chicago Fire,
a pretty good team.
They're very good.
And the LA galaxy, I think, is
the other best team in the States.
That's right.
Now, the United States did
host a 1994 World Cup, and I think
this is where a little bit of
more interest started to come up.
And I think Major
League Soccer was formed
prior to the World
Cup in the United States.
That's right.
Well, there's another part of it.
I mean, as young people, as
children, we almost all played soccer.
I played soccer.
I know a lot of my friends did as well.
It's not popular everywhere,
but a lot of people play it.
And there's not really
an audience for soccer in
America once you're in
the professional realm.
And so the problem is when you
pass the college, you don't think of
it as the NBA, for example, because
there's not as big of an audience.
And so people just end
up doing their normal
jobs as opposed to
being professional soccer.
And I think that has a big something
to do with it is the fact that there
is not as much money in this sport,
professionally as, for example, the NBA.
Or prestige, exactly.
Although this is the, on the other hand, these
players that do make it and they really want
to play, they go abroad and they go play in
the European leagues or something like that.
That's right.
I think a lot of the American
players who were playing the
other day against England were
playing against their teammates.
It's because so many of the
American team, the American
national team play in the
English Premier League.
It was really awkward.
Well, it's a really great sport
as I think it's one of the most
popular sports in many other
countries as well, because it's so easy.
All you need is a ball.
You need a group of people.
You put two rocks and you
have a goal and you start playing.
And that's probably why
it's the most international
sport, because it's
very easy to set up.
People all over the world
love it, and hopefully one
day the United States will
kind of push it and champion.
Yeah. Well, I hope this year
they'll become champions, but
my fingers are definitely
crossed because one of those.
All right.
So it's a really great topic.
We want to know if your
country is in the World Cup.
Have you ever qualified for a World Cup?
There are still many
countries who haven't made it.
Of course, it's a very small
pool, 198, 199 countries
compete to qualify for the
World Cup and only 32 make it.
And you can also tell us
who you're supporting.
We won't judge.
That's right.
So we're waiting for your
comments at EnglishPod.com.
We'll see everyone there.
Bye.